[Music]
thank you
foreign
politics and history and maybe some
other things uh time permitting so uh
before we get into that as always let us
see who are present with us this fine
day or evening or night wherever you are
let's see I can see a parish
foreign
who else
Kiran Creative Planet
Kelly Didi Herbie on Wheels SRI Harsha
binam sarthak edit Abhishek Rohan
Vladimir Hindus harsh
and soulful music in Paris my Lord
and a whole lot of other people all over
the people all right all right so let's
get into the questions with that said
good evening good day all of you once
again okay what are the questions that
we have what are the comments in the
questions let's see um
okay
oh excuse me excuse me so this is not a
question this is a comment
by gunit uh I want to express my immense
gratification for the or for all the
work you do to inform us about the
reality of our world I recently saw your
video on Columbus and how we use the
Native Americans while still being
proclaimed in history later on I did
some of my own research and found that
what you said was absolutely right word
for word this is the first time I have
corroborated what you said and my eyes
were open thank you well thank you sir
for uh for stating this so that's the
thing right my hope is that all of you
will do some fact checking of your own
which will uh which will lead you to the
whatever the truth is right uh see I in
every live stream what I do is I take a
bunch of comments or questions that I
believe will give you the most uh the
most value if I answer that and I don't
do any preparation any rehearsal of how
to answer I don't collect all the
references and evidence I just come and
answer the questions that's what I do
and I it's my hope that all of you or at
least some of you will will go ahead and
fact fact check what I'm saying because
that's how you learn so I can show you
the direction but you need to then take
some steps to learn some more I cannot
spoon feed everybody with references and
sources for everything I I with every
statement I make in every question I
answer I hope that you will do that
that's how you learn that's how you
actually learn how to do fact checking
that's how you learn how to do research
and that's how you learn more history
and more about the world so that's so
it's good to see gurit doing this he has
actually gone ahead and fact checked
what I said and it turned out that what
I said was correct so I hope that all of
you will also do that that's how you
will all learn my hope is that you will
all learn not just the information that
I'm offering you but you will learn how
to learn and learn how to fact check and
learn how to do research so please go
ahead and do that please do that
okay
okay this is uh okay ramakrishna says
you said on Twitter that we are entering
the most dangerous phase of the Ukraine
Russia conflict what do you mean by that
sarthak says please tell how Russia and
Vladimir Putin and plan to end their
conflict what is their main objective
what was their main goal for such a
heavy conflict and costup says now we
know Russia annexed some parts of
Ukraine so so can we assume now that the
war will be over soon
right uh so let's take the third
question first Russia has indeed uh a
next about a fifth of Ukraine the the
nation that used to be known as Ukraine
right about a fifth of the territory has
been annexed by Russia let's take a look
at what those territories are and let's
go to the map where's the map here is
the map where is Ukraine
so
uh some time ago a few years ago Russia
took the peninsula of Crimea so that's
already uh done now Russia so this is
Ukraine this nation here the second
largest nation in Europe apart from
Russia after Russia so Russia has a next
about a fifth of the territory of this
nation right the eastern part and the
southern part some parts of this
southern region are still under
Ukrainian Administration but about a
fifth of the nation has been now uh
formally annexed by Vladimir Putin so
that is done
uh so can we now assume that the war
will be over because Russia has done
this and now the conflict should be over
no well unfortunately the conflict on is
is most likely far from over so that
brings us to the second question sarthak
uh
how do they how does Vladimir Putin plan
to end the conflict what was the main
objective what was the main goal for
this conflict right so you end a
conflict or you work towards an ending
of the conflict once you have achieved
your objectives your military objectives
your strategic objectives and your
political objectives right your
geopolitical geostrategic objectives so
what did Vladimir Putin say say in his
statement when he announced that he was
ordering a special operation in Ukraine
which ended up triggering the Ukraine
conflict he said that he want his
objective is to demilitarize indeed
nazify Ukraine
so not the the notification it's very
simple very straightforward the
ukrainians have this azov division as of
Brigade or whatever they call it and
they consider various war criminals of
the second world war Iraq to be their
national heroes people like individuals
like Stefan Bandera and Nazism support
for Nazism and glorification of Nazism
Neo-Nazi sentiment is pretty much
widespread among the Ukrainian
population in the military in the
government uh
uh I think he even brought a Neo-Nazi in
one of his uh in one of his uh
interactions you know virtual
interactions with some with uh with I
don't know was it the U.N was it Israel
I'm not sure that's the kind of thing he
did so Putin said that he wants to
de-notsify you can that's one of the
principal objectives now has Ukraine
been denotsified uh far from it Ukraine
is not denotified and has Ukraine been
demilitarized Ukraine is not
demilitarized the Ukrainian tank forces
model has gone Ukraine is now depending
on on handouts on charity from the west
from NATO and other other European
nations who are doing this at the behest
of the big uh Puppet Master of the U.S
so uh Aid is flowing into Ukraine
weapons are flowing into Ukraine from
the West yeah and as long as this
continues happening there is no end to
the conflict and Ukraine is definitely
not demilitarized right so yeah so Mr
Putin has not achieved his objectives
yes he has certainly secured
region and whatever other regions of
Interest were for him the places where
you have a Russian speaking majority
right so he has reintegrated those
regions with Russia but the larger
objectives are not yet achieved Ukraine
is not demilitarized it's it's still a
major threat to Russia as long as the
West keeps on uh funneling arms and
other kinds of support into the
Ukrainian military and obviously Ukraine
is not indeed lastified yet so we are
nowhere close to the end of the conflict
right
and now obviously there's the energy
crisis and food crisis that's going on
in the world and especially in Europe
Europe was completely to a very large
extent dependent on Russian energy on
Russian Russian gas and now it seems
like that's not going to happen a
significant portion of the nordstrain
pipeline has been blown up by whoever
yeah it could be this this side or that
side we don't quite know who was in it
nobody has claimed responsibility it
could be NATO it could be the Americans
could even be the Russians for a variety
of reasons so uh so that's a problem
there is still a one of the portions of
the pipeline that still seems to be
functional so there could be gas flowing
in from there if the the two sides can
work things out but there's this massive
energy crisis winter is coming like I
said winter is coming it's going to be a
very cold and harsh winter in Europe the
energy prices are surging they're
becoming really expensive there is
energy rationing in in various parts of
Europe it's gonna be a difficult winter
for the civilian population of Europe so
I I really feel sorry for them but yes
that's how war is waged when the
entirety of Western Europe is arrayed up
against Russia and they are aiding the
Ukraine in their war effort against
Russia the Russians will use all means
at their disposal to pressurize the West
NATO the EU Europe all of that the
United States so yes winter is coming
and Europe is going to be under an
extreme amount of stress
um they are now going to be forced to
buy American Energy supplies petroleum
product it's a great at very high prices
yeah exorbitant prices so that that's
where they find themselves now why did I
say that we are entering the most
dangerous phase of the Ukraine Russia
conflict why why did I say that so
the reason I said this said that is this
Russia has now officially integrated
about a fifth of Ukraine with the
Russian Federation so that territory
let's go back to the map yeah uh so that
territory is now officially
part of Russia that's what Mr Putin has
done uh the eastern part of Ukraine and
the in parts of the south of Ukraine
right around the azovsi and all that and
Crimea is obviously part of that so now
if the Ukrainian military attempts to
retake those regions
then the problem for them is that these
regions now fall under the Russian
nuclear
umbrella any attempt to uh
to uh divest Russia of any of its
territory can be met with nuclear
retaliation Russia does not consider its
territory something that you can barter
away a few pieces here a few pieces
there right if you look at the history
of India since 1947 India under various
uh weak need regimes has been willing to
give away parts of its territory to
Pakistan first of all and then to China
right and there was no real retaliation
when it came to such when it came to
Pakistan biting away at parts of Jammu
and Kashmir or China taking off oxygen
and other parts of Indian Territory
there was no real there were no real
consequences for China and for Pakistan
for these actions when it comes to
Russia Russia will not tolerate an inch
of its territory going to anybody else
somebody tries to do that they're gonna
be met with extreme retaliation and as a
last ditch attempt Russia could even use
the nuclear option
so if the U.S wants to provoke nuclear
war
then they could
order the Ukrainian military to try and
retake the territories that Russia has
annexed and they could send in arms and
ammunition and all that and if the
Ukrainian Army is on the verge of
succeeding Russia may be forced as a
last-ditch resort to resort to to use
tactical nuclear weapons Battlefield
nukes so there's a difference between
tactical nukes and strategic nukes
tactical nukes are low-yield nuclear
weapons uh in the kiloton range you know
the Hiroshima bomb or Nagasaki bomb or
maybe even smaller than that in its
output a strategic nuke is in the mega
tons range one Mega 10 10 megatons the
largest ever bomb was a Tsar bomb with
50 megatons of TNT so those are
strategic news those are ones the new
the news you deploy and you when you
deliver using ballistic missiles
typically typically ballistic myself
tactical nukes are those you use in
battlefields it's never been done but if
the if the US wants to uh escalate
things and make uh and make it appear
like the Russians are the bad guys again
then they could force the Russians to
use tactical nukes on the battlefield
and they could do that by ordering
Ukraine to try and retake Russian
territory Uh Russian next territory and
if they supply enough arms ammunition
all that the ukrainians may even perhaps
be capable of doing that perhaps you
know probably not but they could try it
so whoever strikes the first blow is
always portrayed as the bad guy
in any relationship let's say you you
have a hypothetical couple okay and one
a man and woman let's say right that
sort of couple and let's say it's an
abusive relationship one of these two
people either the man or the woman has
been psychologically emotionally
mentally abusing the other person for a
decade and after a decade finally the
other partner lashes out and and uses
physical violence well no one's gonna
look at the fact that the other person
has been using psychological mental and
other violence on the person for 10
years but the person who strikes the
first blow is the villain
similarly in Ukraine we know what
happened the Americans had been
expanding Eastward slowly slowly slowly
step by step NATO has been doing this
and eventually they crossed Russia's red
lines and Russia was forced to resort to
a military campaign so they fired the
first shot so now they are the ones who
are made to look back similarly if you
want to make them look even worse you
force them to use Battlefield nukes
so yeah they could be entering this sort
of scenario
and that's why I said we are now
entering the most dangerous phase of the
Russia Ukraine conflict and you know the
Western media is now trying to paint a
picture of of nuclear war right I mean I
even read an article somewhere which
said that a small local uh nuclear
conflict nuclear war could even reverse
global warming so they are trying to
portray it as something that is that
could have long-term beneficial effects
so it looks like they are trying to
prepare the world mentally for the
possibility of a nuclear conflict and
once you start a nuclear conflict you
know you don't know where it's going to
go you know uh there are lots of actors
involved in this there are there are
American nukes all over you all over
Europe the Turks on Turkish territory on
on Dutch territory most likely in some
other nations as well so that you once
you cross that threshold the nuclear
threshold God knows where you're gonna
take the world
so that's why I said we are entering the
most dangerous phase of the Russia
Ukraine conflict the Americans uh
they're going to use Ukraine until
they're gonna they're gonna use Ukraine
until the last Ukrainian Soldier is
standing
and the objective is to uh is to weaken
Russia hopefully balkanize Russia right
um they seem to regard right now Russia
as the bigger threat than China and uh
there are reasons why why they think so
and they may be right about this right
now so that's why uh
that's why I think we are entering the
most dangerous phase of this conflict
Russia has annexed territories
if the Americans Force the ukrainians or
order the ukrainians to try and take
that back we could even see nuclear
conflict we don't want to see that but
hey who knows what the superpower wants
so that's why I said that now let's
let's look at it for look at this
further
okay
Russia says will Putin actually use
nuclear weapons in a crucial situation
stuti says as you are aware Ukraine has
blasted the Crimea Bridge do you think
after this incident Russia will use a
tactical nuke to retaliate and ruturaj
says do you think that now Russia will
drop a tactical nuke on Ukraine what
will be the consequences worldwide if
that happens
okay so uh do I think Vladimir Putin
will actually use nuclear weapons in a
crucial situation I think when you if we
have to Define what crucial is
if certain red lines are crossed
Vladimir Putin will indeed I believe use
nuclear weapons he will not straight
away use strategic nukes he will try to
well use the use the smallest new
Tactical nukes but yeah
if certain red lines are crossed he will
definitely use nuclear weapons that's
what I believe right uh now stuti's
question is that Ukraine has destroyed
the Crimea Bridge well uh the entire
Bridge has not been destroyed let's take
a look at where that is uh the Crimea
bridge I think I covered this yesterday
but let's take a look at it again so
this peninsula okay we're looking at
Ukraine we're looking at Eastern Europe
the Black Sea north of the Black Sea we
have Ukraine and you also have Russia
over here and so on so forth the eastern
part is Russia this peninsula is called
the Caribbean Peninsula it's been you've
seen military activity there was there
going back uh centuries yes the 1850s
around there the Crimean conflict and so
on and there's this bridge here which
connects the Russian Mainland to the uh
Crimean Peninsula so uh if this will
ever load yes here we are so this is the
bridge now so now I think about 24 hours
or so ago there was a truck bomb
explosion on this bridge yes and a
portion of this bridge has been been
significantly damaged but the Russians
are working very rapidly to repair and
restore the the
functionality of the bridge right but
yes this is a major provocation and we
don't know who has done it maybe uh
maybe it's Ukraine most likely it's
Ukraine but Ukraine obviously is a proxy
of NATO so yeah that's what's happened
so the question is will Russia use a
tactical nuke to retaliate
I believe Russia will most likely
retaliate in some form in some way at a
time in a place of their choosing that's
that's how things typically go I don't
think they will use a tactical nuke to
retaliate to this provocation to this
incident they will they have a wide
array of tools at the disposal in their
toolkit and they could use anything they
could use uh
a similar kind of a thing maybe you know
a Car Bomb truck I'm not speculating I
have no idea what they could use they
could use something similar they could
use a Cyber attack they could use a
conventional attack uh or something like
that I don't think they will use
tactical nukes it doesn't make any sense
you don't respond to Conventional uh to
a conventional attack with a nuclear
attack you don't do that right so I
don't think Russia will use a tactical
nuke to retaliate to this provocation
but they will certainly respond in some
form maybe disproportionate Force may be
proportionate Force we don't know yet
but let's let's see how things unfold so
we are now entering dangerous territory
do you think Russia will drop a tactical
nuke and so on what are the consequences
um so Russia will not most likely use
tactical news so in what circumstances
will Russia resort to using nuclear
weapons
it's very clear if Russia's territorial
Integrity is threatened then Russia most
likely will not hesitate to resort to
the use of tactical nuclear weapons and
if that doesn't work then they will
escalate further by maybe using more
powerful nuclear weapons Russia has the
largest nuclear Arsenal in the world you
don't want to poke the bear you don't
want to do that and you do that God
knows where things will go right so what
are the consequences worldwide if this
happens well I'm not sure what the
consequences are but nothing good
nothing good
if there is the use of nuclear weapons
then that actually opens up a whole lot
of possibilities that would give the
Americans the pretext the excuse to
themselves you you use nukes against
Russia but if they do that
then that's going to invite a response a
further response from Russia and if they
use nukes against Russia on Russian
territory the Russians will have no
option but to use nukes against the the
United States on U.S territory well that
is nuclear Armageddon once that starts
there's no stopping it so we do not want
to ever see nukes used again the last
time it it happened was in 1945 when the
Americans tested two nuclear devices on
the Japanese population in the cities of
Hiroshima and Nagasaki we don't ever
want to see such a horrific War crime
happen again
so I hope that some sense will prevail
all kinds of nonsense is being printed
right now in the western media kind of
preparing the public for some kind of
nuclear exchange we don't want to see
that so uh yeah so my my understanding
is very clear that there are certain
very clear red lines that Russia has if
those red lines are breached they will
definitely use nuclear weapons unless
and if those red lines are not breached
they will not use nukes the red line is
Russian territorial Integrity somebody
tries to tamper with that somebody tries
to uh balkanize Russia or to
break away any portion of Russian
territory the Russians most likely could
use nuclear weapons right so yeah if you
want to make Russia uh to force Russia
to use nuclear weapons all you have to
do if your NATO is um the arm the
ukrainians enough so that they can go
and attack Russian territory Russian
Health territory Russian next territory
whatever it is and try and you know
break some of it away that's the clear
red line that if you do that then the
Russians most likely will use nukes if
they have no other option so that's
where we are
samarth says what are your views on
India supporting Armenia with weapons
against Azerbaijan sending a message to
Turkey and Pakistan can India form a
trilateral Alliance India Armenia and
Israel
good question
so yes one we do hear the report that
India is going to India has a
LinkedIn agreement or India has agreed
to sell about a quarter of a million
dollars worth a quarter of a billion
dollars worth of weapons weapon systems
Etc arms elimination whatever it is to
Armenia in their conflict against
Azerbaijan right so yeah so India is
supporting Armenia India is not
supporting Azerbaijan
now Azerbaijan is a proxy of Turkey
let's take a look at the map to
understand what is happening there
because the map is our best friend uh
I'm sure you've heard that somewhere
before so where's the map let's take a
look at where this is you know where
India is yes you do let's go westwards
Pakistan Afghanistan Iran Iran Iran
and then you have the Caucasus region
the you have the the Caspian Sea and you
have the Black Sea and in between you
have the Caucasus region kavkas that's
what the Russians call it so over here
you have Iran we know we all know Iran
is it is our neighboring Nation there is
temporarily a temple a temporary State a
temporary Nation between us but Iran is
our neighboring country west of Iran
north west of Iran you have Azerbaijan
in Armenia and then to the west of
Armenia you have turkey so what's going
on here look at the map
so this is Armenia right now if you look
at this little place over here south of
Armenia if you type if you if you click
there it says Azerbaijan so this
territory has been taken over by
Azerbaijan with the help of turkey right
so if you click very close to the Border
through the so-called border here it
says Azerbaijan you click on the
Armenian Health territory over here
it says Asia so apparently Google seems
to be supporting uh Azerbaijan in its
claims that this is azerbaijani
territory and army not Army Integrity
even if you click here it says Asia
right but if you click over here it says
oh it says unavailable so yeah there's
there's some confusion going on here and
Google seems to be playing certain games
now what is the deal so Azerbaijan is
the aggressor they have been
perpetrating all kinds of horrific
atrocities on the Armenian people we
know the history of the Armenian
Genocide starting from the late 19th
century all all the way into the first
quarter of the 20th century yeah
multiple waves of genocide against the
Armenians done by the Turks the Turks
hate it when you speak about this but on
the other hand they don't they they
waste no opportunity to remind the
Armenians Armenians of what they did to
them so they don't want it to be
recognized officially the Turks that
they did a genocide against the
Armenians but they their politicians
keep on making statements and reminding
the Armenians that you know this is what
we did to you and we could do it again
so behave
right so India is supporting Armenia now
the question is who
is India sending a message to Turkey and
Pakistan so first of all please
understand Pakistan is an unknown entity
it is a proxy state of the US and China
there is no point sending a message to
Pakistan Pakistan is is some is like
with the greatest of respect to the
Pakistani people I have nothing against
them but Pakistan is a dog for hire it's
an attack dog for hire that's what it is
it's a goon For Hire there is no point
sending a message to someone's guten you
have to send a message to the master
so to whom is India sending a message
well the question is can India form form
a trilateral alliance with India Armenia
and Israel first of all Armenia is not a
powerful Nation there's no point forming
an alliance with a nation that is is on
the verge of catastrophe one can support
such a nation but an alliance is done
between
more or less equals right uh
now the question is Israel isn't it my
dear friends Israel are you all aware of
the fact that Israel is supporting
Azerbaijan
in this conflict are you aware of this
fact India has been Israel has been
supplying drones
you know those loitering Munitions Etc
to the azerbaijanis in their war against
Armenia isn't it strange that this
Turkish proxy Azerbaijan is being
supported by the Israelis
and the Israelis are are essentially
betting on and investing in the
destruction of this
wonderful ancient Nation Armenia
so why what's happening here why is
Israel supporting Azerbaijan yeah and
why is India supporting Armenia what's
happening here aren't India and Israel
the best of friends according to most
people
What's Happening Here
so let me answer what's Happening Here
it's all about geography it is all about
geography that's what geopolitics is
about you cannot understand geopolitics
unless you see the map and understand
what's going on here and this is also a
lesson for my fellow YouTubers who may
be watching this
geopolitics is nowadays a big cottage
industry in India okay here's the lesson
let's look at the geography to
understand the geopolitics we have this
nation here Iran
okay Iran is a sworn enemy of the United
States we know this
to the north we have Russia Russia is a
sworn enemy of the United States the
Americans want to destroy Iran they want
to destroy Russia we know that very well
who is Israel's number one Ally
it's the United States
the United States is Israel's number one
Ally Israel exists because of the U.S
without U.S support Israel would not
exist understand that turkey is a NATO
member turkey has U.S nukes on its
territory
Azerbaijan is Turkey's proxy by
extension Azerbaijan is a NATO proxy
Georgia is is desperate to enter NATO
they they are against Russia so here is
the geography all right Ukraine is a
NATO proxy all these nations in Western
Europe are NATO are essentially U.S
basal States turkey is a US visal state
with a few Imperial Ambitions of its own
right
the U.S wants what does the U.S want the
U.S wants a bridge between turkey and
Azerbaijan so that it has clear
unimpeded access to the Caspian Sea the
problem is this little Nation called
Armenia Armenia is being supported by
Russia
and the U.S doesn't like it and so what
the U.S wants to do is to create a
conflict here and destabilize not only
the entire region this the Caucasus
region but also destabilize Iran and
Russia hopefully anaheed Armenia and
create a pan Turan Corridor a Turkish
Corridor between turkey and Azerbaijan
and you know they also have Nations like
Turkmenistan which you know could
actually be bought out by the Americans
if the if the price is right or if the
situation is right so that's what's
going on here they are trying to once
again
you know uh become a major player in
this region they have moved out of
Afghanistan and they essentially moved
out of Central Asia some time ago but
now they are trying to create a corridor
over here by by essentially uh wiping
Armenia of the map and there are all
kinds of horrific atrocities that are
that are being perpetrated on Armenia by
the azerbaijanis Yeah the standard
standard turkic standard Turkish
brutalities uh if you if you not don't
know about it well I recommend you don't
read about it because it's it's stomach
churning and yeah there are all kinds of
reports on social media including
Twitter I would recommend don't look at
that anyway that's what's happening so
India is supporting Armenia India is not
sending a message to
turkey or to Pakistan India is sending a
bigger message to the United States that
we're not going to support your nonsense
here so essentially what we are
witnessing now my dear friends is a
complete real and realignment of the
global order India is no longer in the
U.S camp
India is no longer in the U.S Camp India
will cooperate with the U.S if certain
conditions are met
those conditions are not being met all
right the Americans are not are not
concerned about what India wants so
India is now supporting Armenia it's a
message to the United States Israel is
it's not that important unfortunately
Israel I mean uh you could say Israel to
to put it to put it uh to put it kindly
is a junior partner of the United States
I am not using the V word out of
difference to our Israeli friends but
yeah Israel is the junior partner of the
US Israel does whatever the Americans
tell it to do Israel's foreign policy is
an extension of U.S foreign policy and
Israel serves a very important purpose
for the U.S in the Middle East region
understand these things this is the
geopolitical lesson right here
so Armenia is now being supported by
India I expect Iran will most likely
support Armenia and Russia we know does
support Armenia right so this is the new
emerging geopolitical realignment
because the United States is hell-bent
on undermining India's national interest
India is now going to support Armenia in
this matter and we are witnessing a
complete Global realignment I'm telling
you this the decade of the 2020s is
going to be a decade of very fast change
very rapid change a complete realignment
of the global order and a lot more is
happening so this is what's happening
over here so that's why India is
supporting Armenia with weapons against
Azerbaijan it's not a message to Turkey
or Pakistan turkey is a NATO
member state right it's it's uh it's
trying to break free of complete NATO
domination yeah but it's still a NATO
member state turkey is playing you know
a triangular kind of uh thing they they
are uh trying to woo Russia in certain
aspects they're also trying to remain on
the side of the U.S uh and so on turkey
has geopolitical Ambitions of its own uh
Mr erdogan wants to become wants to
recreate the Ottoman Empire
so Azerbaijan is there is there attack
dog in this in this particular situation
so whatever is happening is not a
message to Turkey or Pakistan it's a
message to Nato to EU to the United
States India cannot form a trilateral
alliance between India Armenia and
Israel Armenia is not even strong enough
to be an ally of India it could I mean
we do sympathize with Armenian that's
why we are helping them but it's not
going to be in a line
Israel well Israel is an extension of
the U.S in in most intents and purposes
right I I do wish them well I do hope
that they can have an independent
foreign policy someday right now it's
not quite the case not quite the case
okay sujit says does
um
will India and China go to war in 30
years and atharva says is a Russia India
China Ric Alliance possible
okay so will India and China go to war
in 30 years you know India and China
could go to war next weekend or next
month or next year or sometime in the
next decade 30 years is too long a Time
Horizon for India and China good war
going to war as India arises and as
China stagnates the Chinese may become
desperate and look for you know and
um
look look to give their people a reason
to support to keep supporting the
Chinese Communist party and whoever this
is the Chinese emperor at the time right
now is Mr Xi Jinping who's the de facto
emperor of China
China is not doing well anymore
understand that like I said there is a
complete realignment of the global
geopolitics geopolitical system at work
right now it's happening right now so
what is happening what is happening it's
all been triggered not by the Ukraine
conflict but something that happened a
couple of years before that
what happened two years ago what
happened in late 2019 there was a virus
that spread across the world right the
coronavirus we some people call it the
Wuhan virus the kovit virus whatever you
want to call it the Wuhan coronavirus
the pandemic which uh first the reports
first came out in 2019 and then 2020 was
a disaster 2021 was a disaster 2022
right now we were limping back to
normalcy kind of and then Ukraine
happened the Ukraine conflict uh
happened so
what did the coronavirus pandemic do
whom did it hurt the most it it sent the
whole world into a recession it it
rendered Millions maybe billions of
people jobless it destroyed economies it
caused all kinds of chaos worldwide in
every nation in in the first world in in
Europe in the U.S also in China also in
India lots of people suffered Millions
hundreds of millions of Indians like
they barely survived this kind of
pandemic not because of the illness but
because of the shutting down of the
economy it was a disaster worldwide
India of course did much better than the
other nations in supporting its
population anyhow that's a whole
different story so the coronavirus
pandemic brought China ground it ground
China down to a halt the economy they
showed they put out some numbers that
look encouraging but now we see that
China is not doing well economically the
bigger problem it caused for China is
the complete shutting down as more or
less of the one belt one road OB or
initiative or the belt and Road
initiative the Bri so what is the Bri
thing right let's take a look at the
obor and Bri and all that let's take a
look at that that was China's great bid
for world domination it was their great
bid for super power status in 2008 the
Chinese decided that now is the time now
is our time for for uh trying to become
a superpower our time is now and we have
to grab the chance so they launched this
one belt one road initiative which was
supposed to connect China through
Central Asia to Europe yeah and it also
had a maritime you know the maritime
Silk Road uh component which would
connect China to all these other nations
including Africa so they would get key
resources minerals and all those things
from Africa they would use African labor
and they would also build a massive
connectivity with the whole of Europe
and that would integrate China's economy
with the European economy and other
things and that would be what leads
China to becoming the number one economy
in the world and that would ensure that
they become the superpower and the U.S
declines right
but so that was the great hope the great
ambition of the Chinese the coronavirus
pandemic derailed that
it derailed that all the work stopped in
these regions then you had the Taliban
thing which happened in Afghanistan the
Americans withdrew from Afghanistan that
uh set the whole place for some time
into chaos right there was a lot of
instability there so that also
contributed to this slowing down to the
grinding to a halt of the obor thing
right and now
we have the Ukraine conflict so once
again this Eastern Europe region is
completely paralyzed you don't even see
planes flying to do too much over the
region and now further you have the
energy crisis and the food crisis these
are these have been essentially created
artificially yes you blow up pipelines
you try to impose price caps on Russian
petroleum products you impose sanctions
on Russia you ensure that no food grains
flow out of Ukraine and so on it's gonna
cause a global energy crisis a global
food crisis is who is it going to affect
the most is Europe is going to suffer
this winter we know that it's gonna
affect the global South even more the
so-called third world Africa is going to
suffer
Africa is going to suffer and China
seeks a great amount of resources
minerals and other wealth from Africa
and cheap labor as well so that is not
going to work so this has essentially
derailed China's superpower Ambitions
right so that's one thing that's
happened the other thing the Chinese are
hoping for is that as a consequence of
the Ukraine conflict with Mr Putin
started well he started but he started
it in retaliation that's a whole
different story I've spoken about spoken
about it a long time many times so
China's great hope was that as a
consequence of the enormous massive U.S
sanctions on Russia Russia would have to
come begging to China for help and then
Russia would become China's wasall state
junior partner and China could then
impose very uh one-sided uh conditions
on Russia and then reduce Russia to
another Africa you know use Russia for
for resources and cheap labor and all
that and enrich itself at Russia's
expense so that would again boost
China's superpower Ambitions even though
the obor seems to be dead so the belt
and Road interface is already like it's
it's collapsed
but Russia could serve as the as the
counterweight to that so China was
hoping that Russia would become there
was all state and they could use Russia
to enrich themselves and become a
superpower the problem is this
despite all the sanctions Russia is
thriving first of all they've done well
with the ruble they've uh attached it to
the price of gold the ruble is the gold
standard now so the ruble is doing well
it's in demand and all that and secondly
as soon as the sanctions were imposed on
Russia
they found
they found in a lie that Allah was India
India overnight increased its oil
purchases from Russia 50-fold 50 times
so that way Russia did not have to
depend on China
right and once the other thing that
happened is that India revived the the
what is it called the the uh North South
transport Corridor between India Iran
and Russia let's take a look at that
ntsc north south transport Corridor what
is that
okay a statutory warning as always
Wikipedia is not a reliable uh source of
information but just for convenience
sake I'm putting this up over here the
international north south transport
Corridor is a multi-modal network of all
these things between India and Russia
the starting point is Mumbai one end
point is Mumbai the other endpoint is
Moscow right it passes through Iran it
also passes through Azerbaijan and so on
so this is the thing
so because of this because we have
restarted this it's going to again uh
act as a pressure release valve for
Moscow for Russia so India is buying
massive amounts of petroleum products
from Russia mainly crude oil 50 times
more than it was it was doing and India
is restarting this this thing which the
Iranians essentially had stopped now
Iran is also Cooperative with India in
Russia in this so India
ensure that Russia does not have to go
begging to China
Russia is now standing on its own with
the help of India in in Iran yeah that's
what's happening so India is not
entirely broken has not entirely broken
off with the West India is still part of
the of the Quad India is still part of
various initiatives with the U.S the I2
U2 initiative so India is now acting as
as a bridge between
between
um the East and the West that's what's
happening
and India is now emerging as a major
major power because of all these uh
actions and all these decisions it is
taking yes it is vitally important today
for Russia the existence of India so
India is now whether you like it or not
some people may disagree with me India
is now a great power it's already become
a great power
but obviously this is a very dangerous
situation for India you know India is
still a reasonably small economy three
point whatever 3.6 trillion dollars GDP
and our military might is also not that
large it's something that's proportional
to the GDP we do have nukes which kind
of helps us so that is the situation we
find ourselves in Russia is is not
collapsing Russia is not going to be
balkanized Russia has has enough uh
strength of its own and India is helping
it out when it comes to the economy and
all that
so
because of this the Chinese find
themselves kind of sidelined none of
their hopes aspirations have have worked
out for them they are not going to
become a superpower anytime soon their
economy is crawling they're built and
Road into interface initiative whatever
it is is is is dead in the water they
have not been able to turn Russia into a
wasall state Russia is strong Russia is
stronger than before yeah whatever
you're here you're hearing in the news
please don't trust it don't trust the
Western media and don't trust the Indian
media which is echoing the Western media
so this is where we are India and Russia
have emerged strong a lot of it but we
have major threats now now though the
U.S looks at India also essentially as
as an adversary but yeah it was it it
anyway looked at India as an adversary
it simply wanted to use India for some
time as a counterweight to China now all
these things happened they are now
focusing on Russia because Russia scares
them more than China China is now no
longer Rising as it would have or should
have so that's where we are
so we are seeing the belligerent
response of the US they are trying to
shake up the entire global economy they
are they're printing
billions and trillions of dollars in
their raising interest rates which is
destroying all the other economies the
Euro has crashed the the the pound the
British pound is crashed the Yen has
crashed India and China's currencies
have gone down 10 so yeah they are
trying to you know sow chaos in the
world they have created this artificial
fuel crisis and the food crisis
so that's what we see so right now it
looks like India Russia China Iran may
have to band together in some way or the
other but India and China can never ever
be allies
can never be allies at best we could
have some kind of arrangement of
convenience like we have between Russia
and China today Russia and China if you
look at the map they can never be alive
because they share a long Common Border
in a disputed border it may not be
disputed right now but it's a it's a
dormant dispute the Chinese would like
to reopen it whenever it it suits them
uh yeah so Russia and China share a very
long border it's been a border on which
they've fought they almost went to
nuclear war once Russia had decided to
Nuke the Chinese and the Americans saved
the Chinese so India and China also have
this long undemarkated border we can
consider the Nepal border as also as the
India border and so on so yeah India and
China can never ever be allies we can
never have a good relationship as long
as Tibet is in Chinese hands but there
could be a temporary uh you know
arrangement of convenience for some time
as long as the bigger enemy threatens
both uh so essentially whether some kind
of arrangement between Russia India and
China happens or not Iran will also be
involved if it does happen so whether
such an arrangement or some temporary
Alliance happens so not all depends on
what action what course of action the
United States takes if the United States
uh if the U.S does things that threaten
all these nations at the same time then
you could have these nations banding
together coming together for some for
some time you know in order to withstand
the threat together yeah but if the U.S
is smart enough they could play One
Nation off against the other and there
are lots of
lots of tools they have in their toolkit
you know they are Past Masters that
divide and rule the US is an extension
you know it's a continuation of the
British Empire the British were renowned
for their divide and Rule uh policies so
yeah that's where we are is uh an
alliance between Russia China India
possible most likely not but yeah if the
U.S force forces everyone's hand then
you these nations may come together
along with Iran which is a very strange
assortment of bed fellows you know but
yeah it could happen but uh do not ever
make the mistake of thinking that India
and China can be friends or have good
relationship or have a good relationship
as long as Tibet is under temporary
Chinese occupation simply can't happen
but yeah we could have some kind of
alliance or arrangement of convenience
which would be temporary in nature
okay this is a whole bunch of questions
Vishal Alka manmat and a lot of other
people ask this question Vishal says why
did India not vote against China at the
unhrc Alka says why does you India
usually abstain at Human Rights
resolutions of the unhrc China Russia
Sri Lanka Venezuela Etc significant one
was substantial at the debate and so on
xinjiang China yeah that thing and all
that and manmat says India recently
abstained from voting in the U.N motion
against China's xinjiang region
atrocities and minorities what's the
reason India is trying to Signal
something to the U.S
Okay so when it comes to any
geopolitical action which is like voting
on some matter or something on in the
U.N or not you don't vote based on
principles you speak you know when you
make statements you talk about
principles because we believe in these
principles and we we believe in rules
and we believe in all that but when you
vote or when you make when you do some
action it is always something that's
going to maximize
the benefit for you
it has to serve your National interest
values
and all those things and principles and
all that that's that's only for show
it's only for talking
so when it comes to voting
for or against something or abstaining
on something you have to do a cost
benefit analysis if I vote Yes what do I
gain from it
and what do I lose if I do this if I
vote no what do I gain and what do I
lose and if I abstain what do I gain and
what do I lose right so that's what the
Indian government does
in the past it may not have done this
but this government certainly does that
everything is based only on serving the
national interest that's what it is so
the Indian government would have done a
cost benefit analysis of all three
scenarios voting for voting against and
abstaining and it clearly decided that
abstaining is the best course of action
for India now we may not understand why
because we don't have all the data that
the Indian government has the Indian
government has access to secret
information to classified information
they have I I expect they would have
wargamed various scenarios for the
future
we just discussed whether India Russia
China Iran can come together in the
future for for whatever purpose for a
temporary Alliance or arrangement of
convenience now
that's what it is we also have to
consider the the relative strengths of
the donations economics trying military
strength and all that there's a whole
range of factors and data that go into
making a decision
and based on all this the Indian
government decided that it suits India's
national interests the best to abstain
from voting in this thing we will not
vote for China or against China we will
just stay out of it right this is not
non-alignment this is pro this is pro
India this is this is being aligned to
towards your own National interest now
we may not understand why they've done
it and we are not supposed to understand
why they've done it all the information
in the world is not available in the
public domain there are secret
considerations that are taken right so
so all I can tell you is that based on
whatever the Indian government
calculated
yeah the foreign Ministry the prime
maybe the Prime Minister maybe some
other officials a lot of data would go
into the into into the into considering
this so based on all that based on the
cost benefit analysis it was decided
that it suits India's it serves India's
national interest the most to Simply
stay out of this matter right so you
know and we we Indians tend to be very
emotional about things or minorities
China is doing this and all that it
doesn't matter
what China is doing or not doing in
let's say xinjiang or Tibet or wherever
else is not important right now the only
thing that matters is India's long-term
National interest India's long-term
prosperity and security that's the only
thing that matters
So based on that based on those selfish
considerations we have to make our
decisions right and let's say we vote
against China
it feels good that yeah they showed
China their place in the world but think
of what the second order third order
12th order uh effects of that could be
you have to look at it from a 10-year
perspective right so I am not sure what
went into making this decision what
factors what data points what
considerations went into it but I trust
this Indian government I trust the
foreign Ministry I trust the external
affairs minister the Prime Minister and
whatever they've done must be for
India's national interests so so based
on such such considerations I would may
they would have made this decision
foreign
OPEC have decided to cut down oil
production in a meeting held in Vietnam
Vienna does this what does this mean to
Europe having such a meeting at the
heart of Europe the winter is about as
winter is coming and all that what can
the Euro what can Europe do or the US do
to OPEC what impact does it have on the
Indian economy uh samarth also has a
similar question it seems like Saudi
Arabia and Russia are working together
to manage oil markets what are your
thoughts on this and what will the West
do now will EU be forced to come at
peace with Russia by the upcoming winter
harita says uh what do you make of the
current situation between the U.S and
Saudi Arabia do you think Saudi Arabia
is trying to break free of American
control over their sovereignty
interesting questions so yes what's
happened is that the OPEC uh group got
together the organization of petroleum
exporting countries they got together
and they decided to uh cut down or
reduce the production of oil by
approximately two percent the Americans
had been exhorting them to do the
opposite of that they wanted the OPEC
countries to increase oil production but
they have decided the OPEC group has
decided to cut down oil production by
two percent so they have gone against
the wishes of the Americans right so
what's going on here
so let's understand what what the
background is
um
so you had the covid crisis right the
two years that we all lost yeah the
whole world was locked down during this
time there was a very significant
decline in demand for oil so oil became
incredibly cheap it became at some point
in time I remember it the price went to
below zero so they would actually give
you money to acquire oil that's a whole
different story let's not go there but
yeah oil prices became really really
cheap during the Kobe crisis
then you had the Ukraine conflict then
then the covet thing is started going
down and the oil prices started again
Rising somewhat then you had the Ukraine
uh Special Operation ordered by Mr Putin
which sent oil prices skyrocketing oil
prices really shot up and during this
time Saudi Arabia became one of the uh
fastest growing economies in the world
because of the high oil prices and high
demand for oil
then then you had a a new wave of covet
in China because of which demand went
down and now the Europeans and the
Americans are trying to put a price cap
on the oil that they buy from Russia
which means you the Russians cannot sell
oil to them above a certain price the
Russians obviously will not uh sell oil
to anybody who insists on a price cap
and all that and now you have inflation
you have all these problems so the uh
so the oil prices the the gas prices in
the U.S are quite High there is
inflation and there is the midterm
elections midterm elections coming up in
November this year right which is very
crucial for the Republicans and the
Democrats both to the Republican party
which is currently in power Mr Biden is
in power apparently so they were
exhorting Saudi Arabia in the OPEC
countries to increase oil production so
that the oil prices go down in the U.S
and they can hopefully win the midterm
elections and the Saudis have done the
exact opposite OPEC has done the exact
opposite which could possibly make it
harder for the Republicans to win the
midterm elections this November right so
that's what's happened so uh
so by uh cutting down on oil production
there will be increase in the oil prices
and that's going to help the economies
of these nations so what are the
consequences of this first of all it's
going to help Russia
uh so it will be harder for for Europe
and essentially for Europe to insist on
an oil price cap on vis-a-vis trading
with Russia because you know if if there
is less production then they may be
desperate to buy oil from wherever it's
available
so it will become harder for them to
impose sanctions and to punish Russia
for for for acting in its own National
interest
so that's the consequence on Europe it's
going to uh it's it's not it's it will
the effect will be that it will not the
inflation will not be alleviated in the
U.S unless the US does something
dramatic and oil prices will stay high
in the U.S gas prices will stay high
which is going to make the people
unhappy because people don't like high
gas prices you know the gas prices have
shot up quite a bit in the U.S
so that's the deal so these nations will
benefit from that this and yeah Russia
will also benefit from this so uh if it
is something that that helps Saudi
Arabia it helps the open countries it
helps Russia it is detrimental to Europe
it is determined detrimental to the U.S
the Americans are not going to be happy
especially with Saudi Arabia who
essentially has always been there there
was all state yeah Saudi Arabia was
created by the British and when the
British Empire's Power Center travels
transferred from London to Washington
the Americans took over control of Saudi
Arabia and they have essentially uh
uh treated Saudi Arabia as a client
State and they have forced Saudi Arabia
to buy incredible amounts of U.S weapons
yeah and indulge in various conflicts in
the region to keep the Middle East on
the boil and Saudi Arabia has been there
reliable and Perpetual supplier of oil
and petroleum products now Saudis are
having they're trying to act independent
that is dangerous that's dangerous not
for the U.S it's dangerous for Saudi
Arabia right I I hope Mr MBS Mohammed
bin Salman knows what he is doing
because
you know you go against the vision of
the US especially when you are our South
State who knows what can happen
remember Iraq Iraq was the U.S result
State they propped up Saddam Hussein
they turned him into a great guy they
gave him weapons to fight a war against
Iran there was the great the Iran Iraq
war of the 1980s both Nations suffered a
lot eventually there was a ceasefire
yeah and then when Mr Saddam Hussein
started acting on his own you know what
happened to him
right so uh I hope Mr Muhammad bin
Salman knows what he is doing he is
going straight uh head on against the
dictates of of his Masters the United
States he's going against the U.S
national interest that is a dangerous
dangerous game for Mr Mohammed bin
Salman to play uh so yes it looks like
they are trying to break free at some
level from American control over their
sovereignty which is I well it's
dangerous now what is the effect on
India
as oil price as oil uh production is
reduced oil prices will go up which
means prices of petroleum products of
petrol of diesel of of whatever else is
going to rise these prices will rise in
India which means the prices of all
Commodities will rise in India yeah
that's that's what India is going to
face as well that's just how it goes
these uh
when when these things happen they have
a global ripple effect so it's uh India
should should be prepared for this that
prices of all essential things of food
stuffs of everything essentially will
rise to a certain extent in the coming
days weeks months yeah that's where we
are this is all part of the big Global
game of geopolitics we are witnessing
the OPEC nations are trying to go
against the will and the wishes of the
United States Mr Muhammad Salman is
taking a very very bold step over here
uh so what's going on does he have some
big Nations support we know that India
and Saudi Arabia have excellent
relations now yes uh there could be
something uh Brewing between the Saudis
and the Chinese the southern the
Russians Russians are clearly benefiting
from this right now China seems very
quiet doesn't it the Chinese seem to be
very sideline sidelined and they have
their own internal matter to deal with
the the Ascension of Xi Jinping to
another five-year term yeah his crowning
is the you know the confirmation of his
crowning is the Emperor he disappeared
for some time then he reappeared briefly
a whole lot is happening right now in
the world so yeah so that is what the
OPEC uh oil production cut is about and
that's the kind of
ripple effect the kind of consequences
it's going to have immediately on the
world immediately or in the in the near
upcoming future and what is gonna what
kind of effect it will have
geopolitically for the leadership of the
OPEC countries for Saudi Arabia and
other associations for Muhammad bin
Salman uh remains to be seen but it's a
dangerous gamble they've taken as a
dangerous game they're playing
especially Saudi Arabia
right this is the
right this is the the main question
actually for today and this is just I've
just taken three but I think dozens of
people have asked similar questions
about this particular matter so this is
by param vir aniket and Deepak
barometer says on Jaipur dialogues you
had said that we could possibly see some
conflict between India and the United
States what kind of conflict were you
talking about some economic stuff or
something called warrish
aniket says the Visa issue two-year wait
for an appointment in Mumbai in Delhi 29
days in Chennai is that an accident
Deepak says is America's recent
inclinement inclination towards Pakistan
like the pool of the F-16 package the US
Envoy visiting Pakistan occupied Kashmir
and referring to as so-called Azad
Kashmir Jammu Kashmir is it the response
a response to India not taking any stand
against Russia despite getting constant
pressure from the west from the U.S
yeah so uh this all is happening you
want to take an appointment for a Visa
let's say you're in Mumbai it will take
you more than 800 days for the
appointment date to come you want to
take it in Delhi similarly more than 800
days in Chennai I don't know what it is
29 days I'm really surprised it's 29
days then everybody will go there so in
India it's like 800 days like two and a
half three years to to get a Visa
appointment
you go to Pakistan it's gonna take you
three days to get a Visa appointment you
go to Beijing it's going to take you
three or four days or maybe two days to
get a Visa appointment in India it's
going to take you more than 800 days so
it looks like the Americans don't want
Indians to get U.S visas they are trying
to decouple people-to-people
relationships the people-to-people
relationship between Indians and
Americans there's a huge Indian presence
in the US more than 300 American
citizens are of Indian origin 300 sorry
more than 3 million Americans American
citizens have Indian origin yeah and
there's a very large Indian diaspora
there on visas work visas and all that
in the U.S uh so it looks like now
they're trying to decouple India and the
U.S the People to People a relationship
of Indians and Americans the Americans
are trying to do that so that is
something to note yeah then we have the
fact that the Americans haven't had an
ambassador in India for more than years
possibly more than two years that's
unheard of they don't have an ambassador
in India more than a year maybe two
years the last U.S ambassador was uh Mr
Atul keshab who was who is of Indian
origin after he left there's been no U.S
ambassador
imagine that not not having your
Ambassador in one of the world's major
Powers one of the world's major Nations
it's again designed to send a statement
of some kind to India and now we are
we're witnessing this uh all of these
hostile actions against India India
doesn't arm any nation that is an
explicit enemy of the U.S India doesn't
do anything that explicitly and and
clearly is a threat to U.S national
interests in in a military way
the Americans are arming Pakistan they
are offering Pakistan a half roughly
half billion dollar upgrade package for
Pakistani F-16 fighter planes which will
be used in a future war against India so
the Americans are this is a clear
hostile action then the U.S ambassador
to Pakistan visits Pakistan occupied
Jammu and Kashmir and refers to it as
so-called Azad Kashmir it essentially
means that the Americans are supporting
Pakistan's claim on this region right so
they taking sense they have reopened the
Cold War Playbook they always have been
accusing India of having a cold war
mentality Cold War mindset and what is
this they are doing that they are doing
they are doing precisely what they have
been accusing India of doing right and
India has never taken any such hostile
actions against the US so the Americans
are now
if you if you put all these things
together they are now treating India as
an adversary Nation
right they don't want any more people to
people contacts between India and the US
you want to go for a tourist visa you're
not going to get an appointment for I
don't know more than 800 days so no more
Indians coming to the U.S they are
issuing uh travel advisories to their
citizens about coming to India that
India could be dangerous to travel to so
you know once again you will not see too
many Americans coming to India October
November December up to February March
or whatever it's a tourist season about
six months of the year you know the cold
cold climate when you have in India
that's when most uh tourists come into
India from the US Western Nations and
other parts of the world so you may not
see so many Americans coming to India
this time
so we are trying we are witnessing this
attempt to decouple and and you know
break off relations between India and
the US no diplomacy they have an embassy
in a consulate yeah they they have an
embassy and they have consulates but
they don't have an ambassador so that's
very strange yeah so no diplomatic
relations at that level at the level
which is appropriate for two major
Nations and all these hostile actions
against India
uh or all of that right
so what's happening
so what's happening is very clear India
is acting in its own National interest
India is
India is unwilling to to allow the
Americans to dictate India's foreign
policy
India is saying we will do whatever is
best for us for our national interest
does if it means that we will we have to
buy oil from Russia at discounted prices
we will do that we will buy 50 times
more oil than we were buying earlier
because we're getting it at a good price
if it means that we will reopen a trade
arrangement with Iran we'll do it in the
past India bowed down to U.S pressure
and and stopped buying oil from Iran
which we were getting at a good price at
a discounted price India and Iran had a
very good relationship with oil oil
purchases right so India stop buying oil
from Iran which was very detrimental to
India's national interest into India's
energy security and all kinds of such
things have been done right by the
Americans they India was bowing down to
U.S pressure India is no longer doing
that
and because India has stopped acceding
to all these American demands that's why
the Americans are now treating India as
as an adversarial Nation
right and obviously India acted as a
massive pressure valve in in releasing
the pressure of Western sanctions
against Russia that's what allowed
Russia to stand on its own and not
become a complete Chinese massage State
yeah so India saved Russia essentially
India essentially saved Russia and Mr
Modi essentially saved Mr Vladimir Putin
otherwise Mr Putin would have become a
junior partner to business and China
would have gone on and and continued on
its trajectory to becoming uh the next
superpower
so that's what India has done India has
completely rebalanced and reshaped the
world order to a significant extent and
now America is officially most likely
seeing India as an adversarial State as
an enemy State and now we are beginning
to see all these actions that the
Americans are taking are taking which
they've never taken before uh unless
we're talking about the cold war in the
Cold War yeah they did that they
financed Pakistani terrorism in India
for decades yes the Americans did that
all the terrorism was being financed by
the U.S and so many Indians died in that
so now we could possibly
see something like that happen again
then maybe that's why they are giving
those advisories about terrorism and all
that but yeah this is a different India
if Pakistan if any terrorism is funneled
into India through Pakistan there's
going to be a massive retaliation this
time yeah we don't care about the
Pakistani nuclear status remember that
brahmos Musa that found its way into
Pakistan
yeah these are you know
some people say it was it was a mistake
in some uh Army officials were
court-martialed and suspended or
whatever it's nice to know that we we
have to make such statements yeah but
you don't send a brahmos missile into
Pakistan by mistake you simply don't do
that so this is a whole different India
but yes we are witnessing America now
beginning to treat India as an
adversarial state so I said that we
could possibly in the future see some
kind of conflict between India and the
US what kind of conflict conflict exists
at multiple levels you can have economic
conflict you can have the Americans are
even beginning to impose sanctions
economic sanctions on
individual Indian companies on under
whatever pretext so they are now setting
the stage for more sanctions in the
future
be prepared for this
yeah so now it's begin they have imposed
sanctions on I think one or maybe two
Indian companies for for whatever
pretext they they cooked up yeah
in the future this could uh they could
escalate this so there could be economic
conflict they could impose sanctions of
some kind uh there could be diplomatic
conflict you know there could be
um they could use their various their
entire assortment of vasal states to
pressurize India and to take action
against India they have a whole array of
assault States whether it is NATO
whether it's the European Union whether
it is Australia New Zealand the five
five eyes Nations Canada all that they
also have turkey and Pakistan Pakistan
will do whatever the Americans say as
long as they're paid for it and so on so
so we are witnessing a polarization of
the world order they you could either
have a bipolar gold order we're not
seeing that we're seeing a multiple
world order right now yeah India Iran
and Russia are working together the
Chinese are kind of on the side they are
also to some extent working with with
Russia to some extent but India and
China have a very hostile relationship
right now and we have the entire U.S led
World Order on the other side we are
witnessing multi-polarity France is
somewhere in between they wish they
could break free from U.S control but
they can't entirely break free from the
U.S control the Israelis once again are
America's proxy state in in the Middle
East so is Saudi Arabia
a whole mess we are witnessing right now
and one hopes it doesn't lead to
something really bad
so we are witnessing the beginning of
some kind of conflict between India and
the US in 20 years time it could be a
very polarized conflict who knows who
knows as India arises I think now it's
going to be the U.S that that is more
concerned about India's rise than China
possibly yeah and if China doesn't rise
as rapidly as it wishes to which it most
likely won't then even China may need
India at some level in in some way as a
bulwark against the Western aggression
and neo-imperialism
so we are in the middle of a massive
wide ranging Global geopolitical
geostrategic realignment we are
witnessing right now the emergence of a
multi-polar world order we have one
superpower which is the U.S one failed
superpower which is China
and we have two great Powers India and
uh Russia we have a couple of medium
powers like Iran and France France is
still actually part of NATO in the EU so
it's not entirely a major power but yeah
that's what we are seeing in the future
it's quite possible there could be
conflict between India and the us at
multiple levels diplomacy
uh sanctions economy who knows what else
who knows what else
in 20 years the world is going to be
completely different maybe not even 20
years maybe in this decade itself we
will see a whole different world order
emerging so yeah it's it's still like
what's going to happen we still don't
know and it's it's uh not advisable to
make significant predictions but yes we
are witnessing the emerge of emergence
of this sort of conflict yeah it's it's
most likely gonna get uh more intense as
the
days months years go by
all right
sripad says what's your opinion on on
India offering India 30 stake in a gas
field found by India Iran together and
India has 90 days to respond this gas
field was discovered by India by ongc I
believe ongc videsh or whatever it's
called the company in 2008 2012 maybe
2008 India discovered the Indian company
discovered this oil field this gas field
sorry uh let's see where it was
discovered let's take a look at the map
it was discovered in the Persian Gulf
region so let's go towards Persia we
have the Strait of Hormuz and then we
have the Persian Gulf so it is uh
somewhere in this region in the middle
of the screen somewhere around there
that this uh gas field exists it's
called Farzad B the Farzad B Gas field
and
this gas field was offered to India
there was negotiations negotiations that
went on for years and years and then the
Americans imposed various sanctions on
the on the on the Iranians
excuse me just give me a second let me
drink a gulp of water
right
the Americans impose sanctions on the
Iranians and they forced India to break
off all these relations with Iran and
stop buying Iranian uh petroleum
products and crude oil and all that
so Iran then awarded the contract for
the exploration of this gas field to a
local company
now India is a
India has a whole different geopolitical
Outlook now
we have resumed the north-south
transport corridor
between India and Moscow via Iran via
chabahar also via bandar Abbas
so we are all we are working together
again with Iran we are defying the U.S
dictates and because of that it looks
like the Iranians are once again open to
India
uh exploring and and uh exploiting this
gas field so uh it's offering I don't
know what stake it has offered maybe 30
like it's stated here I'm not sure I
don't know the details but yeah it could
be 30 and they have given India 90 days
to respond which means that you know
respondent 90 days otherwise we'll
assume that you are not interested in
this
I think it's it's fair enough and I
think India should go away with that
if the government feels that it's going
to be good for the national interest
so that's what it is and that's where we
are
how can you guys forgot we have nukes so
I I'm assuming this gentleman or person
whoever it is a person is from Pakistan
and I do refer to Pakistan as a
temporary Nation yes I do that because
it is one like I keep saying I have
nothing against the people of Pakistan I
wish them the best I don't wish them any
harm but Pakistan is a terrorist Nation
it needs to be broken up and sooner
rather than later will be best for the
entire world including its neighbors
India Iran and Afghanistan
so yes I do refer to Pakistan as a
temperature I gave it about 10 years
before it it is uh you know uh before
Justice is done and Justice Means the
people of Balochistan will be able to
determine their future the people of
Sindhu will have will have the ability
to determine their future without the
interference of the of the terrorist
regime the Pakistan Army uh the people
of Hyderabad and Northwest Frontier
Province will be able to uh you know
rejoin Pashto understand Afghanistan
whatever they want to call it and the
people of Pakistan Punjab will be free
of the terrorist Army and the people of
Pakistan occupied Jammu and Kashmir all
that will reintegrate their lives with
India once again
so that's what I call Justice and for
that we have to balkanize Pakistan
hopefully peacefully without any any
violence so that people can uh can can
prosper so yes so that's what I have
said multiple times in this uh person
lady gentlemen whoever it is it says
that how can you guys forget we have
nukes well we haven't forgotten that you
have nukes yeah you don't have nukes by
the way it's your army who owns you that
has nukes
um do you remember the USSR head nukes
and do you remember what happened to the
USSR
there you go
it can be done it can certainly be done
now what happens to the nukes I think
the Americans when they succeeded in
disintegrating the USSR made an enormous
Mistake by not divesting the USSR by
extension Russia of the nuclear weapons
yeah they could not do that and see
where they are today
so uh we will learn the lessons of
history and we assure you that we will
ensure that the nukes are transferred to
a safe location
all right
okay someone says why did Canada issue
Canada Ministry of external Affairs
issue an advisory for Canadians to
refrain from visiting uh Gujarat Punjab
Rajasthan Assam Manipur Etc landmines
exist in Europe and so on look uh
let's take a new new look at the news
report there was something okay let's
just put some news report on the screen
and see what happened so the Canadians
are essentially retaliating to something
India did
uh there have been all these attacks
against Indians in Canada Canada has had
a long history of having a very strongly
virulently anti-india policy right so
the Canadian government has asked its
Nationals to avoid traveling to Gujarat
and so other places The Advisory comes a
week after India cautioned its citizens
justly and wisely from flying to Canada
citing a sharp increase in incidents of
hate crime sectarian violence and
anti-india activities you know and the
Canadians have asked their citizens to
avoid traveling to areas within 10
kilometers of the border with Pakistan
in Gujarat Rajasthan and Punjab so the
Kennedys are essentially saying that
Pakistan is a dangerous terrorist nation
and you if you are within 10 kilometers
of the Border then who knows what could
happen yeah and all that but it is in
response to India's uh caution to Indian
citizens from going to Canada citing a
sharp increase in incidence of hate
crime uh sectarian violence and
anti-india activities so the Canadians
have responded to what India has done
that's that's the deal that's what's
happened right
so yeah this is this is standard uh in
diplomacy a nation takes certain action
and the Other Nation feels compelled to
respond especially when you have a
nation like Canada which doesn't have an
independent foreign policy Canada is
essentially a massage state of the U.S
so um yeah and as as we just discussed
the Americans are now uh
are treating India as as an adversarial
Nation so yeah we will see more of this
happening in the future which is that's
what I that's what I expect
okay what's the next question the next
question is by asmita
Israel and France have been in support
of India in the past at International
forums given the recent developments in
provocative actions from the US against
India what changes are likely in The
Stance of both these nations towards
India
very good question so yes now we are
seeing
this is the theme of today's discussion
isn't it the theme of today's uh
session the uh change in stance of the
US vis-a-vis India the U.S is now taking
multiple actions into very in a variety
of ways which all are hostile actions
against India so they are now changing
their policy towards India they are now
regarding they are now treating India as
an adversarial Nation they are treating
India like an enemy now right we are
seeing that happening now uh like asmita
says Israel and France have in the past
uh more or less consistently supported
India in in certain matters at
International forums and there has been
a lot of cooperation between India and
Israel and India and France especially
from the Strategic perspective and
defense perspective for instance uh
India and Israel have developed uh
certain missile systems together the
Barack eight missile I believe it's an
anti-ship missile and and an
anti-anti-missile missile it's a missile
defense system and so on and and India
is buying various Israeli defense but it
and on a whole lot of other things when
it comes to India and France India has
acquired five French designed submarines
the Scorpion submarines most of which
were built in India itself
and there is cooperation in the Indian
Ocean region from a geostrategic
perspective we may also we are also
acquiring French rafale aircraft yes and
uh there could be some other things also
which may be uh being done right now
which we will not discuss here so yes
India and France and India and Israel
have a very good positive and mutually
beneficial relationship and it's been
that way for a significant amount of
time now we are witnessing the U.S
changing its policy towards India it's
now treating India as an adversary
relation it's essentially treating India
as an enemy Nation
we also know
that France and Israel uh are closely
aligned with U.S foreign policy France
is part of NATO France is part of the
European Union NATO is a U.S Creation
The Top Dog in NATO is the US the EU is
once again a U.S creation the top dog in
the EU is the US the one major power in
Europe in Western Europe is the U.S it's
not Germany it's not France it's the US
and France is the only nation within
NATO or within the EU that has a
reasonably reasonably independent
foreign policy and yet when it comes to
Ukraine and other things they are forced
to support uh whatever the U.S says now
the U.S has changed its stance towards
India what's going to happen to the
India France relationship we don't know
it could go bad it won't happen
overnight but yes things could happen
yeah I mean I'm I don't want to
speculate as to what will happen but
yeah we we have to anticipate such a
thing that that possibly could happen
yeah when it comes to Israel Israel hmm
like I said it's uh to put it uh kindly
Israel is a junior partner of the US you
know the the greatest support from
Israel
world the world over comes from the U.S
yeah uh the U.S has ensured that Israel
um remains safe and Israel is well
supplied with armed civilization all
that Israel obviously is a very uh
entrepreneurial Nation a very
enterprising Nation they've ensured that
they acquired nuclear weapons on their
own most likely yes and they have the
Samsung option they've also developed a
whole range of of Defense technology and
all that so it's not like they they they
have been spoon fed by the Americans
they are a very enterprising people a
very entrepreneurial people of a Nation
that's worthy of a great deal of
admiration right we I think many Indians
if not most Indians admire Israel a
great deal and yet Israel is very much
aligned with U.S foreign policy so if
since the US has completely taken
changed its chance towards India we
could witness uh
you know a change in the india-israel
relationship as well we already know
that India and Israel are on opposing
sides in the Azerbaijan Armenia conflict
Israel supports Azerbaijan India
supports Armenia we are already on
opposing sides in that this is a very
recent development
more such developments could happen I
hope that India and Israel will continue
to have a warm
and good constructive mutually
beneficial mutually uh respectful
relationship but let's see you know
right now there are too many unknowns at
play Too Many parameters that we still
cannot compute so the next uh month the
the forthcoming months and maybe the
next couple of years will will bring in
a great deal of clarity as to what
trajectory the india-israel relationship
is going to take and what trajectory the
India France relationship is going to
take France no doubt wishes that it
could break free
of the Yoke of the American yolk that
has been placed around its neck yeah but
you cannot Escape geography you cannot
Escape that you're part of Western
Europe which is entirely ruled by the
U.S so uh France has to make do with do
the best of what uh whatever the
whatever cards the gods have dealt with
dealt it so yeah
it does operate within a great deal of
within a lot of constraints and all that
yeah so yeah let's see how it goes but I
expect that there will be some kind of
changes in the India France relationship
and the India Israel relationship I hope
that these both these relationships will
continue to be uh friendly and warm and
positive and mutually beneficial that's
the hope but one has to always
anticipate trouble when the Americans
have changed their stance so so I hope
things remain good but let's uh keep a
very close watch on how things go
okay says how can India overcome the
chicken neck problem what's this chicken
neck problem let's take a look at the
chicken Nick problem so we must
obviously go to the map to understand
the chicken neck problem the chicken
neck problem refers to the silly Guri
Corridor so for whatever reason
uh when
in 1947 when power was transferred from
one set of crooks to another set of
crooks the uh the the recipients of the
power transfer which is the Indian
politicians who were beholden to the
British they agreed to uh
to accept this sort of map this sort of
geography which which you know this very
thin strip of land 50 kilometers wide at
its narrowest which connects uh the Far
East of India to what is called Mainland
India and then between uh East Pakistan
now we did a liberate East Bangladesh
from east from Pakistan in 1971 but we
did not change the Border they could
have taken some territory and made this
portion thicker we could have liberated
the chittagam which is chittogram Hill
tracks which are predominantly Buddhist
and the you know they could have been
liberated we did not do those things we
could have even done more because it was
under our control we had conquered the
territory you had the right of Conquest
anyhow that's what happened that's what
uh that's what we have been given by the
events of History so this is the chicken
neck problem
the Far East of India all the the seven
states in this region arunachal Pradesh
nagaland manipuram tripura meghalaya
um Assam Etc Sikkim they are connected
to the mainland part of India by this
very thin Corridor the Siliguri Corridor
and that is what China
always keeps eyeing for obvious reasons
so if they were to you know do a
military operation and succeed in
cutting this off you know in in
capturing this territory it would
immediately cut off the the Far East of
India the so-called north east of India
from the mainland part of India and that
would be a disaster for India right so
that is the chicken neck problem so what
can India do to overcome the chicken
neck problem the long-term solution to
overcoming the chicken neck problem is
to liberate Tibet from illegal and
temporary Chinese occupation yes if but
that is something that India is not in a
position to do anytime soon maybe in the
next 20 years maybe in the next 50 years
maybe sooner who knows we don't know
right now we are not in a position to do
that but that is a long-term solution
that is the uh the permanent solution
liberate Tibet make Tibet independent
again uh liberate it of any Chinese
influence and then the problem goes away
because Tibet is a friendly Nation a
friendly culture they are part of the
extended indosphere and India in Tibet
have never had any issue so if Tibet is
free then the problem goes away
now right now Tibet is under Chinese
occupation temporary and illegal Chinese
occupation and the Chinese soldiers are
right at the border of Sikkim and Bhutan
they they they they are also biting into
Bhutan his territory you know over here
you can see it on the map and so on
and we have Nepal over here so what is
the solution to the chicken neck problem
since we cannot liberate Tibet right now
um one of the solutions is if there is a
war
between India and China in this region
and if the Chinese were to hypothetical
they won't succeed in doing this but
hypothetically if they were to make
inroads in this region we could simply
use the Bengali territory the the
Bangladeshi territory you know so the
Indian army could could simply take over
parts of Northern Bangladesh and simple
that that will fortify the region right
in war everything is allowed when you
are at War you don't look at diplomatic
niceties and the rules of uh you know
international relations and all that if
your territory hypothetically is under
risk of being overrun you simply can
take over parts of Bangladesh and then
use that
to uh to support the rest of the forest
of India so that's the simple solution
and I'm sure the our good friends in
Bangladesh will have no issue against
that because we are the same people same
culture same Origins same everything
yeah we will eventually give it back to
Bangladesh I'm sure we will yeah it's
just a temporary measure so uh I'm sure
about Bangladeshi uh colleagues will be
more than happy to to uh accommodate uh
this this kind request so that is a
simple solution we also have Nepal
so in case we could also leverage some
of the Nepalese territory right the
tarai region there is there is a lot of
hilly region the hilly territory over
there but there is some uh planes as
well region over here so we could maybe
leverage some of the temporarily yes I'm
sure our Nepalese friends will have no
issue with that since we will obviously
be going we will obviously uh return the
territory once it is no longer needed so
yeah we have plenty of options so we
need not worry about this this is
something our our wonderful politicians
including the Magnificent Mr nehru
should have thought about when they
agreed to this including the great Mr
Gandhi as well but yeah this is what
what this is these are the cards that
history has dealt us and we need to have
multiple options to uh take care of any
any situation or any contingencies
excuse me
okay Alpha Beta says excuse me Elon Musk
is ready to turn on the internet in Iran
what do you think about this happening
somewhere so something like this
happening in different parts of India
interesting question so Elon Musk is has
he already done it I'm not sure if he
has maybe he has he did turn on starlink
services in Ukraine and he did say I
remember him saying that he would turn
on starlink internet services in Iran as
well so because of various protests and
demonstrations and things and unrest in
Iran in some parts of Iran the
authorities would have switched off the
internet so if Elon Musk turns on these
are the the starting service then the
people of Iran could be in a position to
to use the internet for free from the
satellites that Elon Musk has deployed
uh in orbit around the Earth
so that's how you can use technology for
geopolitical purposes that's how you can
use uh you know civilian technology
apparently civilian technology for a
geopolitical purposes right so now Elon
Musk is has become a geopolitical player
he can shape the course of actions in
places like Ukraine and in places like
Iran he can undermine the government of
Iran if he wants to by doing this and he
can he can also undermine the government
of Russia if he wants to if he can do
this then he can do this so what about
India let's say in let's consider a
completely hypothetical completely
imaginary completely fictitious scenario
fictional scenario hypothetical scenario
in which in some part of India for some
time there is some kind of unrest and to
restore Law and Order the Indian
government switches off the internet in
the region for for let's say a few days
now what if Elon Musk decides to turn on
starlink internet over there
he is in a position to do that isn't he
well that would be essentially an act of
war against India so you see this is the
kind of
geopolitical uh leverage space
technology gives you space technology
may look like civilian technology but it
always has a military Dimension that's
why it is extremely important for a
nation like India to not be left behind
in the space race in the new space race
India needs
to develop more powerful rockets in
their needs to develop the ability to
launch satellites on demand at short
notice let's say next week I want to
launch Five military satellites do we
have the ability to do that I'm not sure
we do we need to have that ability
we need to have the ability to demand to
to launch Five satellites 10 satellites
next week next month at short notice big
satellites not tiny satellites you know
we need to have that that is a massive
Advantage if you have such abilities so
India needs to ensure it's not left
behind India also needs to develop the
ability to deploy counter measures
against such interference in India's
Internal Affairs so let's say you have a
constellation of satellites I'm not
saying it belongs to to Elon Musk or
SpaceX or whatever but let's say you
have another nation's satellites a
constellation of satellites that is in a
position to deploy to Broadcast internet
services into India if they so wish you
know we should be in a position to
neutralize such satellites through
electronic countermeasures means or
kinetic means or whatever means we see
fit we need to have these abilities and
we do have the technology we do have the
minds to do this
Israel is is is a fantastic organization
you you fund them properly they're going
to give you 10 times the results they're
giving you right now right the only
thing that's holding Israel back is the
funding
so yes this is this is an excellent
question that Alpha Beta has asked us
and this is something the Indian
government needs to please please take
very seriously we cannot be left behind
in any of these matters whether it is it
comes to space launch Technologies
whether it comes to building more
powerful Rockets excuse me whether it
comes to the moon rays you know uh
deploying uh
Rovers and satellites around the Moon
Rovers on the moon surface or ensuring
that we have a human presence in Earth's
orbit or ensuring that we eventually
have a moon base that we inhabited by
human beings by Indian citizens on the
moon all of this needs to be taken very
seriously we cannot afford to be left
behind in these things because all space
technology has a military Dimension and
the geopolitical dimension and now this
question brings it home very clearly so
all space technology can be used in this
manner so India needs to ensure that
whatever uh
the past few years we have kind of taken
it very easy when it comes to space you
know space exploration we need to catch
up and we need to catch up very rapidly
I hope uh things are being planned and I
hope we catch up as soon as possible
all right that's been a lot of
geopolitics because geopolitics is the
flavor of these days these times that we
are living in but let's take some
questions about something else
excuse me
saurabh says many historians say that uh
the Harappan era was urbanized by the
way while The Vedic culture is rural but
many villages were excavated near the
Harappan towns and cities so what about
this think about it like this in the
United States think about the United
States right it's the most uh most
prosperous nation in the world today the
most powerful nation in the world today
do they not have huge cities like New
York City San Francisco uh Atlanta
Los Angeles and so on so forth they've
got big cities they also have small
towns smaller towns they also have
villages
yes but it's not a rural Nation
it's not a nation that's considered to
be rural it's a very high it's the most
advanced station in the world if you if
you
keep Japan apart for for a minute yep
even if you look at Japan they have
these metropolises like Tokyo yeah like
Hokkaido like Kobe
uh and so on yeah lots of big
metropolitan cities they also have small
settlements the thing is that even the
small settlements small town and
Villages are technologically advanced
and very modern
so there is no Nation or civilization in
the world that can be entirely Urban it
can be an urbanized civilization which
means even The Villages are urbanized
they're planned like a big city you may
have only a hundred houses but it's
still planned properly and it's got the
best technology even though it's a
village so it's not like you will not
have running water there it's not like
you will not have 24x7 electricity there
it's not like you will not have mobile
services there it's not like you will
not have internet there you will have
all the amenities and all the facilities
that a big city has in a small village
yeah so even if you live in a small
village you're missing out on nothing so
that's how it was during the the
so-called Harappan era the Saraswati
Sindhu phase of Indian history it was a
completely urbanized civilization a
completely urbanized era a period of our
history you had massive cities like
harappa and all that you also had small
towns you also had Villages but they all
had the most advanced technology and
lifestyle of their time that's what it
was when it comes to The Vedic culture
um I'm not sure if you've identified any
Vedic era sites because most likely all
the sites that we have archaeological
sites were inhabited for thousands of
years but we know from the text of the
rig Veda that the society that is
described in the rig Veda is a pastoral
Society a rural Society there is no
mention of big cities of an urban
civilization right it's all rural
agrarian pastoral so that's why it is
very clearly understood that The Vedic
era
of India of Indian history The Vedic
phase of Indian history was a rural
phase of Indian history the population
was most likely quite small and you had
this huge subcontinent this huge
geography and uh you had various Clans
that inhabited this uh enormous
geography in various parts of the
subcontinent and it was mostly a rural
phase of Indian Australia it was quite
prosperous but we had no great cities
and no urbanization so that is the deal
all right
saurabh says again why didn't Indians
possess Neanderthal genes as compared to
Europeans and Central Asians okay let's
take a look at that
so uh this uh has not been published yet
but uh
uh I think it's going to be published
soon the the these uh these results I
have I had a conversation with Dr neeraj
Rai in in a podcast on this channel you
can look it up so in that podcast he did
say this and he has mentioned this in
other places as well that most Indians
excuse me
that most Indians do not possess
Neanderthal genes excuse me but east
Asians I'm not sure
but Europeans and Central Asians have
these genes so what does it mean and why
why is it so excuse me let me just take
another sip of water
so it's like this
the Neanderthals were a distinct
subspecies of humans they were different
from Homo sapiens but quite closely
related to Homo sapiens so we could
procreate together
so the Neanderthals seem to have split
off from our last common ancestor about
800 000 years before today and the near
the thoughts uh their remains are found
across Europe
and
and their remains are found up to up to
the Middle East region but not least of
that so it looks like for whatever
reason the Neanderthals inhabited Europe
and up to the Middle East but they do
not seem to have been present further
east from there so there are no
Neanderthal remains that are found in
Iran or the Indian subcontinent whether
it is Afghanistan Pakistan or wherever
else and no Neanderthal remains anywhere
in eastern Asia
um
now we know most likely what route our
ancestors who came out of Africa about
80 000 years ago what route they took
they most likely crossed over from
Africa into Asia in this region the bab
al-mandib strait between present-day
Djibouti and present-day Yemen and
Arabia was mostly a desert but the
coastal regions were green you had some
forest or some vegetation there so they
traveled along the coastal regions and
then they once again most likely crossed
over from the Strait of Hormuz right
and do Mainland Asia so they crossed
over into Iran and most likely the
western part was desert but the eastern
part was forested so they kept traveling
eastwards and then they entered the main
the main part of the Indian subcontinent
which was entirely green the Indian
subcontinent is filled with river
valleys very fertile land very good for
sustaining any amount of population so
that's where our Out of Africa ancestors
finally settled down for the first time
this was the first permanent settlement
they stopped migrating for a time after
this so uh the Indian subcontinent is
the Out of Africa Founders Zone and
afterwards eventually the people who
settled down here migrated in all kinds
of different directions and that's how
they populated the rest of the world
from the Indian subcontinent
so when our ancestors traveled out of
Africa and came eastwards they most
likely did not encounter in Indian North
house because the Indian adults did not
live east of the Middle East region they
only lived to the west of that but
eventually out of the once our ancestors
settled in India eventually they they
went into Eastern Asia and also into
Europe and that's when and that's where
they encountered neanderthals and that's
where they procreated with them and
that's how European people
they have between two to four to six
person maybe eight percent Neanderthal
ancestry more likely two to four percent
but Eastern Asian people and most
Indians don't have that so that's how
that's how it happened
to be all right
all right let's take another question
this is by Cherry Berry
namaskar CherryBerry I uh so I am from
Bangladesh nice to meet you sir ma'am uh
I watch your videos regularly thank you
uh yeah so the question is how was our
present day Bangladesh during the
Mahabharata ramayana was our country
known as angadish or something else
during the ancient times
uh so the entire Bengal region not just
Bangladesh but the whole of Bengal
because Bangladesh is one part of the
overall Bengal region so this entire
region was known as angadish during the
Mahabharata Iran most likely uh possibly
before that but during the Mahabharata
it was known as angadish karna was made
the king of our angadish right
so it was known as angadish not just
Bangladesh but also the region now known
as West Bengal so later anger became
vanga it was known as vangadesh later
and then Wanga became Bunga it became
Bangladesh or Bangladesh or whatever
right so that's how the name Bangladesh
and Bengal or whatever else comes from
it comes from anger
uh and anger was most likely one of the
great mahajanapadas if I am not mistaken
yeah it was definitely a janapada for
sure and the one of the ancient Kings of
this region was elected democratically
after a period of Machinery or chaos for
a century or so so you know you have
uh this interesting example of Indian
democracy at work in ancient vanga
history so yeah that's the deal so it
was known as angadish initially then it
came it became known as as a vangadesh
then Bangladesh at some point in time it
was known as gowda also Goda and so on
so it's it's had different names
okay Surya shekhar Panda says it seems
that Buddhism being the only missionary
in in being the only Indian missionary
Dharma immensely projected India's of
Power by increasing India's cultural
ideological intellectual etc etc etc
influences throughout Asia during the
Buddhist era your views also how can
India which hardly has any original
philosophical influence left not only a
global skill but also over its own
people at the present time regain it
okay so uh Buddhism is the only Indian
missionary Dharma I don't entirely agree
with that uh both the Dharma is one of
the flavors of Indian dharma obviously
of Hindu Dharma or whatever you want it
Dharma itself now
um
let's take the example of someone like
Kumar ajeeva kumarajiva was a great
scholar a great philosopher who traveled
to China he's his
father was from Northern India Kashmir
most likely his mother was a Saka
princess I believe from khotan or
somewhere let's let's take a look at uh
can I pull this up there is a wonderful
article by Dr Subhash kak about this
kumarajiva in the middle way in China
let's put that on the screen and let's
take a look at that so kumara Jiva was
not simply a Buddhist scholar a both the
scholar he was also a Vedic scholar so
today the historians portray the
transmission of Indian culture eastwards
into China and Japan and other places as
only Buddhism it was not only Buddhism
so this is an article by Dr Sebastian
who who has appeared on this channel at
least a couple of times kumarajiv and
the middle way in China
uh so uh this is about The Vedic
tradition in Central Asia in China there
are lots of representations of Shiva
maheshwara Uma Krishna Ganesh all those
deities Etc so that's not just uh both
the Dharma it's so it's it's The Vedic
Dharma right
now when it comes to uh kumarajivam
let's see what it's uh his father was
from Kashmir right and uh his his mother
was from Kucha on the Northern rim of
the tarim Basin that's in present day
so-called uh temporarily Chinese
occupied xinjiang so his mother was from
that region but she obviously would have
had some Indian ancestry as well and his
father was from Kashmir uh so um
so kumaraji was studied a variety of
things he studied Buddhist texts of the
service Diva the school he also learned
The Vedas the darshanas ayurveda
astronomy and other sciences and these
callers who went to China would
typically transmit all of this but today
it is all categorized Under the Umbrella
of Buddhism by modern historians look at
Japanese culture the Japanese culture is
a beautiful syncretic culture which
combines Indian dharmic uh Indian
dharmic culture and the uh Japanese
traditional indigenous Shinto belief
system Shinto culture
and that's what Japanese culture is
today the Indian component is called
Buddhism but if you look at Japanese
deities the deities that are worship you
have bin zaithin who is Saraswati
goddess Saraswati you you have kangitan
who is who is Lord Ganesh the god Ganesh
and you have the entire Indian Vedic
Pantheon represented in Japanese
so-called Buddhism so it's not just
Buddhism it's it's just the entirety of
Dharma you look at uh Thailand Thailand
is categorized as a Buddhist Nation they
worship Kali there they worship Ganesh
there they worship Shiva there they
worship all the various Indian gods
there I can show you evidence next time
if you want right I can pull up various
Instagram accounts of Thai people
celebrating Durga Puja celebrating
celebrating Ganesh utsav
so it was Indian culture it was Dharma
that was project that was propagated
throughout Asia not just Buddhism but
today today's historians want to
categorize categorize all that as
Buddhism which is inaccurate and
deceptive all right uh so yeah so that's
what happened so so that's my view about
this but it this was done the
transmission and propagation of Indian
culture throughout Asia and Westwood
also was done primarily under two great
Empires the modern Empire firstly and
then the kushan Empire the the main uh
the person who did it the most during
the modern era was the great emperor
Ashok who transmitted mainly both the
Dharma to various parts of the world so
he sent uh Scholars Dharma gurus Etc to
Greece to to Egypt to the Western World
he sent uh such people uh to Central
Asia to bahalik et cetera to camboge he
sent uh Dharma gurus to Sri Lanka he
said Dharma which is southeast Thailand
Burma all that you know this entire
region
then you had the great emperor kanishka
one of the greatest Emperors of all time
in India and he exclusively focused
mainly eastwards China so with every
single so he he did a massive amount of
trade with China and every single trade
delegation he would send to China with
that delegation he would send the
magurus you know Scholars and and if you
look at kanishka's coinage if you look
at the entire coinage of kanishka you
know they portray kanishka as a Buddhist
emperor
if you see his coinage less than five
percent of the coins have Buddhist
symbolism on them like the God but the
like Lord Buddha or whatever the other
coins have a variety of divinities
mostly Hindu divinities and yet they
call him a Buddhist
emperor so you know our historians have
been trying to deceive us
uh so people like kumaraja were very
Adept they were scholars in in Vedic uh
culture as well right The Vedas and
darshanas and what not
so it's it's this culture that was
Spread spread uh worldwide
and it was done
in two different periods one during the
mainly during two different periods once
during the mauryan period and secondly
During the kushan period
so it happened both times when India was
politically unified under a very
powerful Empire and Emperor
so today India is recovering from a
millennium of humiliation a millennium
of foreign occupation and and brutality
India is still deeply mentally colonized
and that's why we have very little
philosophical influence not only on the
global scale but even within our own
uh people right even our own people you
see what's happening in Indian society
today we are very deeply influenced by
Foreign culture foreign values foreign
religions and whatnot yeah
so how can India regain it so think back
of the times when India was able to
influence the whole world what how what
was India like at the time
the modern era and the kushan era both
These Times India was a superpower the
most advanced and most powerful
civilization in the world
so you achieve that you're gonna again
influence the world it's as simple as
that soft power is merely a secondary
byproduct of hard power
that's the lesson of History
all right let's see something else
pushkar Rai says Have you listened to
the song uh by Marian faithful she moved
through yeah it's on YouTube why does
the music sound so similar to Indian
classical music is there any connection
please please please pick my question
this time all right Marian faithful uh
let me show you something interesting
uh you're talking about Marian faithful
um
this is a tweet that I put out in 2017.
Celtic music and Celtic themed British
folk have a remarkable Affinity with
Indian classical music she moved to the
fair by Marian faithful and there's a
link to a YouTube video so I think this
is a YouTube video you're referring to
and then you have the the uh Irish I'm
not sure if he's Irish but he was
certainly British musician Davey Graham
he was the first among the Western
musicians to realize that there's an
ancient connection between Indian music
and the folk music of Ireland and I have
tweeted about that later as well let me
try and put that up on the screen if it
will load Twitter sometimes loads a
little slowly
it's loading
it's loading so Davey Graham is a theory
that there is a connection between
Indian music he calls it Oriental music
and the folk music of Ireland and to
prove this is going to play for us his
own variation of the Irish Melody she
moves to the fair which is something
that Mary and faithful also sang and
then you have another folk musician with
Indian influences John Fahey he was
American he died he is unfortunately
dead he was a wonderful guitar player
and he also had lots of pieces that he
played that had a lot of Indian
influence then he had Led Zeppelin Led
Zeppelin record an entire album in
Mumbai in 1972 in collaboration with
local musicians that album you you
hardly find it anywhere but yeah uh
there are it's I I'm sure you can find
uh that on YouTube and they popularized
that God guitar scale the guitar tuning
for playing Indian Raga influence music
and obviously you have uh Marian
faithful's music as well so there is an
alternative guitar tuning called The
dadgad Tuning the standard tuning is EAD
GBE so the dart guard tuning is
something that is more conducive to
playing Indian ragas and also Irish
Celtic music so that's what the that's
what Led Zeppelin did they popularized
that uh tuning it was first I think
introduced by David Graham himself
himself so why is there
this connection why does Iration Celtic
music uh sound so familiar to Indian
classical music obviously there's some
ancient connection
there is an ancient connection uh I may
have spoken about such Connections in
the past if you look at Irish the the
founding story of the Irish people the
Irish mythology the
the mother of the Irish ancient of the
ancient Irish mythological people was
the goddess called dhanu he was a river
goddess right and the river God has done
appears in the rigveda as well and the
rigveda clearly comes before any
founding of Ireland so that's the
connection you know it's an Out of
Africa sorry it's an out of India
migration that happened God knows how
many thousands of years ago and you have
an entire bunch of rivers in Europe that
are named after the same God as Dano you
have the Danube the dawn the niper the
nicester
and so so forth the rodanu which became
the Rhone and so many more
all across Europe River after River
after river river named after the same
ancient rigvedic river goddess so
clearly there was a migration of ancient
Indian people out of India westwards for
whatever reason
maybe multiple ways of migration but
yeah one of them were the people who uh
held God has done in the highest regard
and yeah so it all ended up in Ireland
and if you look at the genetics of
Ireland you do find the Indian origin
r1a haplogroup in about two to three
percent of Irish males but you do find
another haplogroup in 86 percent I think
of Irish males which is r1b the sister
haplogroup of r1a
and that haplogroup what are the origins
it's still kind of uh not yet proven but
let our geneticists do their research
and we will have the answers
all right
okay Dash Place says how can one nation
avoid good times and weak people so
what's the what's the thing
uh strong people no
Hard Times create strong people strong
people create a strong Nation a strong
Nation gives rise to good times good
times create weak people and weak people
create hard times and then the cycle
continues
right that's the Imperial cycle that's
what you find in China that's what you
find in India you have a period when you
have an entire empire under Consolidated
under under a single Emperor the morian
era the kushan era and so on so forth
you have the Chola era the karkuta era
and so on and then you have times in
which you the nation is fragmented it is
divided into small kingdoms which is the
you know the the
uh good times and weak people and all
that and the past 1000 Years happened
because we were caught at the wrong time
when we were disunited
so how can a nation avoid such a
situation
Good Times creating weak people look at
the U.S look at the U.S
does that look like a healthy Society to
you
do they what are the what are the values
they're espousing right now
are they espousing greatness are they
espousing Excellence no they're
espousing mediocrity that's what they're
promoting today that's what you're
witnessing in American society today so
good times and weak people that's what
you're seeing right now in front of your
eyes that's that's the way the us is
going for whatever reason right so how
can a nation avoid that the answer is
very simple meritocracy
meritocracy
give
um what it means is that you you
um it's the pursuit of Excellence
you have to
respect the fact and you have to
recognize the fact that everybody is not
equal you have to give everybody the
same rights
but you can't
Ensure
the equality of outcome you give
everybody the equality of opportunity
and you give everybody the same rights
but you cannot guarantee equal outcomes
some people will outperform the others
and you have to reward those who
outperform the others
so that is meritocracy that's why we
have examinations and only one person
can be the first ranker not everyone can
be given first rank that's why we have
sporting competitions that's why we have
the football World Cup we're not going
to give the crown to every single nation
that participates only one is the winner
that's why we're the Cricket World Cup
right the world is by nature unequal
a rabbit is not equal to a lion a
crocodile is not equal to a deer and so
on so forth and even in humans some
people are more intelligent some people
are born more intelligent some people
are born more athletic some people are
born taller and so on and so forth so
and so forth you have to reward those
who perform well you have to reward
excellence and if some people are for
whatever reason not able to do well you
have to ensure that they they they are
still given dignity and equal rights as
everybody else you know so that's the
the Hallmark of a good Society but if
you reward excellence and if you promote
meritocracy
then it is hard for such a nation to
have the situation of good times and
weak people if you're rewarding
Excellence then you are rewarding strong
people the the ones who make the nation
stronger we you don't do that at the
expense of those who are unable to be
that strong you also give them dignity
and equal rights but you reward those
who do well
and and eventually every Empire crumbles
because of this problem because they
become too smug that they think that
they are they're the best and they
become over indulgent and that's what
gives rise to weakness and at some point
in time there is a disintegration of
meritocracy and there is there is
nepotism and all that comes in and
that's the problem yeah so if you have
the right system in place then you can
keep going on indefinitely as long as
you don't
you're not tamper with the system the
right system and sometimes whether you
like it or not Wars are good for a
nation for keeping a nation strong
sometimes I like that I am not a fan of
War I am not saying we should have wars
but if you look at the past ten thousand
years of human history it's a history of
warfare that's just what it is sometimes
sometimes whether you like it or not
worse strength and strengthen a nation
and a people you know that's how it is
so that's just what history tells us so
that's how a nation can avoid the Trap
of having too many too much good times
and to people who which gives rise to to
weak people right
all right I think we will stop with the
questions here I have I have more
questions but I'm I I'm I'm gonna take
some questions now from the live chat
we're going to take a few questions from
the live chat
good God
Che Guevara who claims to be Adolf
Hitler
well okay was samudra Gupta India's
greatest Emperor he was one of India's
great Emperors for sure
so samudra Gupta was his entire career
as Emperor was an extended military
campaign
and he he unified almost the entirety of
India under his dominion and uh he
conquered almost the entirety of
Southern India in a two-pronged approach
using the two-prong two-pronged approach
it was a
a campaign through a land campaign with
infantry and and Cavalry and all that
and a simultaneous Naval campaign using
his Navy he had a powerful navy so yeah
he was a great emperor he unified India
and he was also very good for the people
you know the people prospered during his
Reign even though he conquered lots of
territories and unified the nation there
was no burden on the people the people
prospered even more and it was a period
of great uh cultural and economic and
prosperity and flowering so yeah he was
one of our greatest Emperors
one would also have to say that Chandra
Gupta maurya was one of our greatest
Emperors so was samudra gupta's father
Chandra Gupta the first and kanishka and
Raj Raj and rajendra Chola and to some
extent even
and so on so forth so we had lots of
great Embers India's history is so so
vast and so ancient that it is
impossible to say that one single
individual was the greatest of all time
I mean how can you forget Lord Rama and
Lord Krishna as well Lord Krishna was
not but he was one of the greatest and
most consequential Indians who ever
existed and so on and so forth right so
yeah
okay what else
let's see some other questions
[Music]
um
okay let me address it without
addressing it Karthik says can you talk
about the Chandra chandrayaan two
Landing conspiracy theory you were
referring to on the runway show which
controversy we know that the children
two mission was a partial success we
have an Orbiter which is still in orbit
around the moon and there was a Lander
which did not quite land it it kind of
flipped over at the last instant and it
crash landed on the moon it
disintegrated so yeah that's that's what
happened yeah
that's what happened that's something
more I can say about it
okay
um Rishi says don't you think that the
visa restrictions are a blessing in
disguise these can reduce the problem of
brain rate if made more stringent so
yeah you know all these problems are
opportunities probably a problem is an
opportunity in Disguise so yes if the
Americans don't want to give Indians
visas great thank you very much
thank you very much we will now utilize
our own brain power for our own benefit
but for that the government needs to
ensure that those Indians who want to go
to the U.S and who are not able to go
there they should be uh given
what they deserve in India
they are looking for opportunities and
India is unable to give them the
opportunities in the in the in the
quality of life that they wish to have
and maybe they deserve to have so India
needs to ensure it rapidly transforms
its its internal structure and it starts
giving really good world-class
opportunities to world-class people
otherwise we'll keep losing them
elsewhere yeah so yes it is a blessing
in disguise it's a great opportunity for
India to leverage this situation for its
for the benefit long-term benefit of the
Indian people and Indian civilization so
yes it is indeed an opportunity not yet
a blessing in disguise but certainly an
opportunity to convert the situation
into a blessing yeah
all right let's take maybe one or two
questions
um
Vanos says will you be coming live next
weekend unfortunately I will not be
coming live next weekend I am once again
traveling this this forthcoming weekend
uh I will ensure that I keep releasing
short clips all the every single day so
hopefully that will
tied over the deficit but yeah next
weekend I will not be able to come live
yeah so that's advanced notice of that
and apologies in advance it's
um unavoidable travel I I don't want to
ever miss a live stream but yeah this
time is gonna happen so apologies for
that in advance
uh
uh what else do we have what else do we
have any other questions that I have not
taken before
all right sneha says nowadays everyone
is talking about a U.S recession how
will it affect the ID sector
um
interesting question I'm not really sure
right now how it will affect the ID
sector
when it comes to Indian ID companies
they exist to provide services to
American companies and to American
businesses right uh you write code and
you develop projects and you
maintain software
and stuff for mainly for American
companies yes and if there is a
recession there may be a dip in demand
for various Services let's say you let's
say you're talking about credit cards
and gift cards and all that a gift card
is a card that contains a certain amount
of value maybe a hundred dollars that
you give as a gift to somebody and then
they can use that card to buy anything
they want that's a gift card now if
there is a recession there may be a dip
in the sales of gift cards so that may
affect the IIT sector in so that's just
one example in one one example of how it
could affect American businesses that
could end up in turn affecting the
Indian ID sector that essentially exists
to serve the U.S businesses so yeah
there could certainly be some kind of uh
effect on the IIT sector we especially
when it comes to the Indian companies
that certainly Could Happen yeah
all right
um
let's just take one more question one
more question
why are you always high well do you have
you seen how tall I am so that could be
the reason yeah
okay let's take a serious question
let's take a serious question Maybe
um
let's see
Shaheen says do you know about
an Iranian Trader who's the subject of
various hypothesis
I I've never heard of this person no
very interesting I've never heard of him
I will certainly look into the drop say
is it a girl is it was it a lady
not sure okay I will suddenly check it
out for sure
yeah so that's something I was not aware
of
uh
okay let's see one more question if we
have something really want
relevant uh
manav harif says what's your opinion on
the future of Indian leadership I think
the future seems to be quite bright yeah
the future of Indian leadership seems to
be quite bright one of the uh one of the
characteristics of a really good leader
is that he or she ensures that there is
a pipeline of mode leadership there are
more leaders who are ready to replace
him or her whenever he or she needs to
step down
so what top class leader creates more
leaders who will eventually act as
Replacements and I think we are seeing
that right now in the Indian leadership
uh context so I think the future of
Indian leadership is bright all right
with that we come to the end of today's
live stream thank you very much my good
friends my dear friends my dear viewers
thank you so much for being on this live
stream and for your viewership and for
your support in whatever way thank you
very much I really appreciate it and I
will see you in the next live stream
until then take care
and uh bye